[Music]
so I'm really excited about today's
conversation I'm joined by two former
stars of the channel in McGilchrist and
John Vevey key and you both have I think
very your vote both very comprehensive
thinkers you both have a really
interesting big-picture take on the
world which I'm really looking forward
to hearing you you guys explore and
compare notes
Ian people may be familiar with you
wrote a book called the master in an
emissary that was hugely influential it
looked at how the left and the right
brain perceive the world differently and
how that kind of that difference
cascades through culture and cascades
through all of human knowledge and human
history and John you've become kind of a
cult hit in the last year or so with
your series called awakening from the
meaning crisis which again is this very
big picture appreciation of the kind of
grand sweep of Western culture where
we're at and where this sort of meaning
crisis that we're in how we might start
to look at getting out of it so I hope I
did justice to your you're both of your
work there but I'd love to ask you maybe
intern what you would like to inquire
what you'd like to get out of this
conversation and what you'd like to ask
the other about their work maybe
starting with you John
what I'm interested in talking with you
about um first I think there's I do work
on plausibility so this interest may be
a little bit specific to me and but one
of the things that brings plausibility
to a theoretical stance is when you have
sort of independent convergence on a
position and I've only really very
recently read reading in fact it's the
reading Ian's book and so I came to
conclusions about the hemispheres from
doing the work I do on insight and it
seems to me that they're deeply
convergent with the ends especially the
emphasis on attention and how the
hemispheres should be thought as almost
cano ting an entire sort of existential
mode and so I'd like to
a little bit about that yes I use sort
of some problem-solving language to talk
about it
he's a slightly different language but I
think it's we're seeing the same things
I just want to quickly explore that sort
of set up a common ground and then what
I'd like to talk to Ian about are he
says some tantalizing things about
reason and rationality which are big
topics for me right now because as you
guys know probably you might know from
the series and some of the work I'm
doing I'm trying to expand the notion of
rationality take it out of being located
into a sort of just logical inferential
management and expand the notion of
rationality to try and once again
reintegrate it with wisdom and so the
topics of rationality and wisdom I'd
like to talk to Ian about that the
important roles for example that insight
and implicit learning perhaps play in
rationality and and then the overlap
with wisdom takes us into their topic
that I'd like to spend the bulk of the
time talking about which is this idea of
the meaning crisis and what I'd
specifically like to do is and this has
to do more I think with the timing of
Ian's book so in the last 15 years and
I'm part of this there's been a lot of
psychological and cognitive scientific
work on meaning in life and how that's
different from like semantic meaning and
what are the factors that drive meaning
in life and I thought it might be
interesting to bring Ian's work and that
cognitive science and meaning life into
a deeper discussion so those are the
things I thought we could talk about
well that certainly gives us enough to
chew on for a few days I'd be very keen
to explore those things and perhaps also
what it means to know something and what
it means to understand things you know
these word you know bandy about but they
have different meanings in fact I often
think that one of the reasons so my kind
of American philosophy goes off into
what I consider a rather autistic and
sort of left hemisphere dominated realm
is because we don't almost
q Lily alone have different words for
different kinds of knowing man and that
was this fight a lot of confusion so I
would certainly like to talk about all
of that I like to talk about that Ian
because I'm doing a lot of work now it's
been through the series and I'm
developing it more on the sort of four
kinds of knowing and as you say you see
in other cultures they have different
words for these different kinds of
knowing and and we could perhaps touch
on that because I think that plays a
central role in the MTG crisis the loss
of the theoretical connection and to a
significant degree even the embodied
lived connection with these other kinds
of knowing other than the propositional
knowing that is so prideful American
culture so I would like to really begin
to that very deeply could you listen
ways of knowing John just the way I
talked about the way I talked about it
is that there is propositional knowing
which is the one that is belief centric
and propositional knowing is knowing
that and then you fill in a proposition
knowing that the cat ISM is a mammal and
this of course is highly prized because
it's the center of sort of inferential
theory building and and we'vewe've tend
to do assimilate everything to that we
even treat religious systems as if they
are systems of belief even though there
are good people out there like John
Kahrs James Carson you know the
religious case against believe saying
that's a serious misrepresentation of
what's going on in religion now
cognitive psychology and cognitive
science have sorted started to open up
to the second P which is procedural
knowing which is knowing how to do
something like how to catch a baseball
and here the normativity isn't the
conviction of truth right which you have
for propositional knowing here the
normativity is a sense of engagement and
empowerment right so it's the aptness
the fitted nurse of your skill which is
very different kind of normativity
skills don't - or false they are apt or
well fitted or not
then there's perspect honorable knowing
this is the knowing that you have
because you are a conscious being this
is knowing what it's like to be here
right now they here now knows what it's
like to be sober what it's like to be
saying what it's like to be awake what
it's like to be conscious sort of my
salience Landscaping how things are for
grounded back rounded write all that
dynamics
and sizing up and on getting sort of an
optimal grip as normal Ponte talks about
honest situations so this is basically
your situational awareness and so the
participatory knowing is it's the most
back rounded it but it's the deepest one
it's the one that a lot of post writing
Aryans have been trying to bring into
deeper awareness it's this sense of
attunement fundamental connectedness
being at home it's the sense it's the
sense you lose when you're in another
culture that the you your agency and the
arena just aren't quite in sync the way
they need to be and so that is
ultimately the the grounding that that
sort of CO identification process that's
happening in participatory knowing and
so for me two things that tried to work
some audience question deep
understanding is involves an alignment
of these four kinds of knowing that's
deep understanding and I think a lot of
the meaning-making machinery where
meaning doesn't mean semantic content of
your propositions but it's your
fundamental lived sense of how connected
you are to yourself to other people into
the world ultimately takes place in
these lower the procedural the
perspectival and ultimately the
participatory kinds of knowing and our
culture has lost deeply lost theoretical
touch with them and I think in many
people's lives they've lost a kind of
lived existential touch with them sorry
that was a lot but I tried I need to
cover quite a bit great and there are so
many things that I'd love to pick up in
what you say I start with the idea of
what a belief is which we consider to be
the essential or not
to a logical proposition of some kind
the root of the word believe is in life
actually it's in yeah believe and err
yes yes believe in and it's is to do
with a relationship and that central to
what you're talking about what I'm
talking about because truth can be
thought about
correctness to an abstract idea that we
have or it can be truth in the sense
that a person can be true to another
person or to set the carpenter makes are
true to one another which means that
they meet and that there is some sort of
coming together so I would see the big
fault line in knowledge to be between
the is and the I thou in the Masters
emissary I suggest that the evolution of
language very much wrongly promoted a
relationship of standing back and an I
it even though it began in the business
of wanting to communicate mmm and so as
John Archibald wheeler said I mean it's
there are many many conferences between
physics and a decent philosophy this is
a participatory universe even at the
hardest edges of physics what is as it
were we conceived out there and what is
in here not fully separable it's not
being put together with other people but
we're already together it's just that we
imagine the separations and that are
much less vivid than they seem to us in
the way in which we think so I think
what's happening in the world were in at
the moment is a kind of dis embedding an
abstraction a D contextualizing and this
is typical of the way in which the left
hemisphere thinks it is very acts who
construe a model that is internally
consistent that is not necessarily
consistent with experience and it would
take too long but I've written it much
more about it in the book that I'm just
finishing this week which has taken me
about ten years to talk about this
business of our being decontextualized
from the body from the continuity of a
car
from the spiritual realm and all that is
implied in that and from togetherness
with the natural world all these things
which are so important to a sense of
meaning our lives of have until just a
few hundred years ago for millions of
years they have been embedded in nature
and you know I hate the word the
environment because it suggests that
nature is something around you but
you're not here we are nature we can
amount of nature to go back into nature
there is no division there between us
and is it I don't know I hate that it's
like that talking about God as it almost
the professor says she but anyway and so
I think that what's happening is it's
not surprising there's a crisis of
meaning because meaning comes not of
constructing a serial line of words
thoughts and ideas that leads to a
conclusion very much the left hemisphere
way of thinking but emerges without our
being able fully to understand how or to
control the process out of a being
embedded in dwelling him as Heidegger
would have said the world and in that
sense we are now deracinated from as I
say from our culture from nature from
one another from the body so much
nowadays is so purely put across as
abstract and cerebral the way in which
psychologists and neurosciences talk
about the brain is perhaps inevitably
but I think very damaging leak outs in
language entirely appropriate to a
machine and it's very hard therefore to
stand back from all this talk of
circuits and switches and replays and
relays and so on to the notion that the
brain is actually an aspect of a person
so I'll just put all that out for the
moment that's wonderfully rich Ian so
I'm gonna now speak as a representative
of a movement I suppose you could call
it within and cognitive science because
I clearly identify with this
just called 4e cognitive science I don't
know if you're familiar with it but this
is the idea that we have to
fundamentally break out of that sort of
Cartesian model both that the mind is
locked inside the head and it's a pure
logic machine and its primary operations
are epistemic in nature so right but the
fact that that you has been given the
fact that that has just been translated
into sort of materialist view is still
radically insufficient so what forty
cognitive science emphasizes is the ease
that we have to see cognition as
inherently constitutively embodied we
have to see cognition the next e as
inherently constituent embedded we are
it is the way in which we are coupled to
the environment the dynamic coupling the
mutual unfoldment of cognition and
environment in which we should
understand cognition that it is extended
that cosmic cognition isn't in the head
especially distributed cognition that
most of our cognition our
problem-solving is done in concert with
other people networked together so
there's deep interpenetration between
culture and cognition and then finally
enacted that cognition isn't primarily
about argumentation it's something that
we view by basically evolving the
sensorimotor loop on a step by step
basis and that's where in fact I do a
lot of my work and so a lot of this work
I think is actually deeply consonant
with the criticism you make of what is
still like I agree with you it's still
sort of the paradigmatic way in which
that Cartesian paradigmatic way in which
we see people investigating cognition
but to maybe give you some hope because
that what I'm trying to for econ of
science is a big deal and it is becoming
it is growing in prominence and
importance it has you know we've just
released you know there it is the Oxford
Handbook of for e cognitive science
right so for T cognition so there's a
lot that's happening now but that I
think has
two things behind it one I think is a
bona fide scientific academic
realization of important aspects of the
functionality and phenomenology of
cognition and consciousness that cannot
be addressed adequately within that
Cartesian creamer so I think there's a
genuine philosophical scientific body of
argumentation that is just pushing us
out of that and it's been deeply
influenced by you know Heidegger the Neo
Haida carry-ons but I think also and
this is something I argue in my series
I think this turn isn't just purely
epistemic Lee driven it's not just
because people are trying to solve
problems I think there's a big cultural
motive behind this that there many of
these people myself included we are
practitioners of various kinds of you
know Ecology's of practices like I do
you know various kinds of mindfulness
and Taichi and stuff like that because
right we're trying to see if we can
reunite if you'll allow me a bit of a
slogan here the science and the
spirituality back together again
that's I think what's really happening
right now in a very deep way well you
know I like all of that and as you can
imagine I'm very much on side with that
there is nonetheless a tendency at a
master level for for that to become
itself a rather disembodied theory so I
like the emphasis on praxis and on
movements yeah one of the themes I mean
my latest book which would we call the
matter with things which is a pun on
several levels no it could have been
pretty much called everything flows
because we tend to see the world as a
series of snapshots or elements or
slices that are cooked together as our
conscious cognition puts ideas together
rather than those slices or or snapshots
being if you like illicitly extracted
from what is an always seamless flowing
process so you've probably seen to her
skis recent work on the same thing
I wanted to talk to you about some of my
most recent work because it just goes
directly towards you just what you just
said you know trying to get past this
snapshot version of reality so myself
and Dan Jaffe we're doing work on how
the scientists the NASA scientists on
earth make use of the Rovers on Mars
you know the Rovers that are exploring
and what they get is they get back
snapshot pictures that's all they get
and they don't have joystick control of
the rover right and so they can't
actually do the science with those
snapshots what they're what they look
for is somebody who can do this and I'll
talk about it in a sec they do these
sort of tricks with their mind so that
they can get a sense of actually being
on Mars and the person can go from the
snapshot to the being on Mars they look
for the scientists that can do that
because those are the people that could
actually do use the rover as well to do
and what's really interesting they want
that sense of presence that perspectival
knowing and so what they do is you can
see them and and they just do it
spontaneously they generate that
participatory morph knowing they first
of all they Antep remise them the
rover's instead of saying the rover
should go here they say I should go
there and there and we should go there
right and oh no I'm stuck here right and
but they also techno morph eyes
themselves though do things like those
like they'll say yeah I'll go put a
phone on a desk you say there's the rock
and they'll go like this for the cameras
and I need to do this I need to and they
swivel and move their body around right
and what they do is they they get this
right this loop they're sort of shaping
their anthropomorphizing the rover and
rover Ising themselves with Ulen army
and they create this participatory bond
and you know what's really really
interesting is they'll say things like
this these are these hard nodes left
hemispheric rational theory builders
they'll say things like you know what is
working in the garden and my right wrist
got sort of stuck and when I got to the
lab the Rovers right wheel was stuck and
they'll even say I don't know what's
going on but there's some kind of
connection basically we have to build
perspectival and participatory knowing
before her they can do any of that
sophisticated theorizing and that puts
me in mind as I'm sure it does you of
how a skilled tracker puts himself into
the frame of the animal yeah they're
just traffic so he can see what it's
seeing and be know where he's going
so I think that is that is wonderful to
get back though to well let me just give
you some idea of of what I've been
writing about if I may it's very fresh
in in my mind at the moment and I can
deal with the first part of the book
very briefly I basically look at the
ways in which we garner knowledge of the
world all the time and the main conduits
through that can happen wick through
extract can happen namely attention
perception the judgments that are bound
up with perception cognitive
intelligence and social and emotional
intelligence those are the ways in which
we can sort of get information knowledge
about the world and that's a very long
story short in a sentence each of these
I compared the role of the right on the
left hemisphere what comes out is that
the the left hemisphere is more is less
good at all these things it's it's more
sitting in a place where once the right
hemisphere has dealt with experience it
can take it away and do procedures on it
in the second part of the book I look at
what I would call the four routes to
understanding which are a more long-term
process whereby we try to make sense of
what it is we've with me know through
those those modes like justice right and
I believe they are science reason and I
would distinguish being reason and
rationality here intuition and
imagination and my conclusion again very
briefly is that we need each of these in
almost every case
to be applied to what we're looking at
there are some exceptions but in reality
what's happening is that we're using
only one or perhaps two of these
modalities in approaching any subject in
order to understand it and what's more
we're relying most on the perks of the
left hemisphere contributes which are
less valuable than the parts that the
right hemisphere contributes including
to science and reason the myth that
somehow science is all left hemispheric
well the reason is it completely wrong
and then in the last part of the book I
look at the building blocks of the
cosmos time-space motion yeah
consciousness matter value and the
divine and and a coincidence the
opposites is my last chapter which is
very strong theme in the whole book and
really what I'm suggesting is we
misunderstand the world because we're
using only a tiny fraction of what we
could be doing and knowing largely
because we've got locked into this in
fantastically restrictive reductive
mechanistic very simple way of thinking
about the world in which is modeled on a
machine and you know it's just not like
that I don't know where there's so much
I want to respond to on that so I do
something very similar I'm getting sort
of really surprised about how convergent
our work is so I where I start as a
scientist is I start with a central
problem of attention which is the issue
I call which is the issue of relevance
realization which is of all of the
information available to you what do you
Syrian on is relevant how do you make it
salient out of all the information
available to you and long-term memory
what do you access and how do you how do
you shape it of all of the possible
combinations of things you could do all
the courses of action
all of these search spaces are
combinatorial explosive and they all
right and and they all require an
amazing ability which which is the thing
that we're finding most difficult to
give to you
artificial intelligence was the exactly
disability of somehow not searching the
whole space because that would take way
too much time somehow you intelligently
ignore which sounds like a Zen Cohen you
intelligently ignore most of that
information and reliably no we're
perfectly because you can't nobody can
be perfect on this and that'll bring me
down to something I want to talk about
you zero you reliably zero in on
relevant information now that tells me
right right from the beginning this is
the point I want to come back to their
cognition and knowledge should not be
held prey to logical standards of
certainty because that is not actually
cognitively possible if you try to lodge
it your way through all of this
information processing you would commit
cognitive suicide in fact most of your
cognition right can't operate that way
so this for me carries in a deep
epistemological implication which is we
have to give up and think about how
deeply entrenched and you probably say
this is a left hemispheric thing I think
not given some of our email exchange we
have to give up the standard of
certainty in you know as how we evaluate
truth and perfection is how we
understand goodness I think those two
standards have held us prey in a really
disastrous way and so part of what I've
been trying to do then is okay once we
we make this is we have to understand
that this relevance realization
machinery is happening pre inferentially
but before I can make any categories I
have to be able to zero it right so we
so I call this this this ability to be
coupled to the world and relevance is
transient this is relevance is not a
property of this right it's not a it's
not just a subjective thing
it's an affordance between it's a real
relation between me and so this is I
call this religio it's the sense of deep
binding and I'm alluding to one of the
ideological potential etymological
origin of religion right and I see a lot
of practice that people have dismissed
as irrational as practices that are
designed to activate and accentuate this
sense of religio so where that takes me
to is and
and I want to pick up on two points in
your book that I think are relevant is
back to and maybe you're using reason
how I use rationality maybe we may just
have a semantic thing because I think
the core of what I call rationality is
not inferential manipulation of
propositions right because that's
ultimately this logical thing that's I
think it's put it's a it's put us in the
wrong model of how we're trying to get
knowledge because I think what
rationality is ultimately about is this
idea the very process is that of our
intelligence that are doing this
relevance realization are also the
processes that can it can misfire and
they can make the wrong thing salient to
us in the wrong way and I think that is
sort of the key of self-deception and
you've pointed out two things that I
want to bring it back into what I'm
calling rationality perhaps what you
mean by reason you noted how you know
the right hemisphere is very good at
looking for when it has went where
there's anomalies or where things are
going wrong whereas the left hemisphere
is this sort of no no things are right
stick to the formal system right and so
the right hemisphere would play a very
deep role in overcoming self-deception
and where that I think we've got
experimental evidence for that is the
following as you note in your book I
think correctly in insight we overcome a
Mis framing and what we do is we go into
the right hemisphere we don't try and
solve the problem anymore we actually
try to change the framing of the problem
and then we come back and it's
increasingly looking like the machinery
by which we gain insight is also the
machinery by which we overcome
self-deception so self-deception seems
to be this breaking out of inappropriate
framing and that means that there's a
lot more things that are central to what
I'm calling rationality than
argumentation the all of the things we
need to do all of the practices we need
to gauge and so that we can
systematically call our self-deception
into real question and also to aspire
teach truly transforming in the face
that challenge that's what I want to
pack back into the notion of rationality
because at the heart of it even at the
heart of science the scientific sites
isn't about the sets of propositions it
collects it's about a self-correcting
process that's designed to try and help
us overcome the way we're self-deceptive
that's what should be made that should
be made the keystone of what I think
we're talking about when we're talking
about being reasonable or being or
pursuing rationality so that's that's
what I want that's what I want to bring
to bear because I think there's deep
connections between a reformulation of
rationality a rediscovery of the kinds
of knowing and then this what you're
talking about
about these kinds of projects of
knowledge acquisition if I can put it
that way I think there's they need to
talk to each other very deeply Wow
there's nothing for it we just have to
have many more of these conversations
which to go to first there's so many
things I want you to pick up on
first of all certainty certainty doesn't
exist certainty is just one of those
fictions it would depend on the idea of
truth being as it were a thing out there
that we can grasp where is truth this
coming together of things which is
always a matter of negotiation so we
negotiate with reality and we change the
gestalt that you'll see we don't add
another thing to align we're pursuing
instead we shift the gist out the whole
picture and then we see more and what a
Turkish tout is is simply one that
explains more than the one we've just
jettison was able to in fact when I when
I was in my twenties I wrote a book
about literary criticism which listen in
the end called against criticism but I
thought of calling it against perfection
it seems to me that the problem with so
much of the way we philosophize about
everything including the arts is to have
abstract ideas that we wanted to
approximate to rather than seeing the
thing as having an individuality which
we couldn't have forced in and we
couldn't predict it and which gives
something to the world
so I'm absolutely with you on that on
self-deception and well as I say in the
book and in that book and I say more
about it in the book I've just finished
the left hemisphere is a master of
self-deception I mean except that it's
not in a master because it doesn't know
it's even doing it but it is capable of
deceiving us in the most extraordinarily
gross way and you see this in in you
know hard neurological cases where
people will deny the most obvious
realities because they don't have
insight and we know that when patients
who've lost insight because of an
illness start to get insight into their
illness this is because bits in the
right frontal cortex with the left
hemisphere is quite capable of getting
further and further into a thing it
believes to be right and the only way to
free it up is to the right hemisphere to
be able to intervene and say hang on
hang on
Ramachandran calls it the devil's
advocate because it's the one that
detects the problem so yes I think we
can be very self deceived and one of the
interesting things is that you know of
course the work of Dunning and Kruger
the dunning-kruger effect are just for
the sake of the audience I just said the
dunning-kruger effect is an observation
that the people who are doing worst at a
subject and don't really understand it
think they know it all and have a gross
over estimate of what it is you know
whereas the people who really know
rather doubt them so yeah the
observations in follow-up experiments
after the initial experiment and set of
experiments showed that when they had
got a rational schema for how to
approach something they were more and
more confident that it was right even if
the model was blatantly wrong so I think
well that's very relevant to the way in
which we so many of the things we get
passionate about or to do with a very
simple theory or model
how the world should be but not about
how from experience the world is and I
suppose the thing that's most important
out of what you said at least for your
as I understand your concerns is about
reason and I'm making a distinction
between rationale we don't have this
proper distinction in English but in
other languages like Greek and Latin and
German there are distinctions between
China's of understanding yeah but we as
again we don't distinguish different
kinds of knowing we don't distinguish
different kinds of understanding yes
well one is an understanding which is
purely schematic the kind of thing that
a computer equipped with an excellent
lexicon and the rules of syntax would be
able to do whereas there is a kind of
reason that doesn't in any sense what
should I say deny that but combines it
with the precognitive implicit intuitive
sense of things that you were describing
in which 99% of our knowledge actually
resides with that schema and the way in
which it is employed and in a way it's
like the difference between you know
putting a lot of data into a computer
and allowing the computer to decide
what's going on the data are selected by
you before you put them in and when they
come out they're interpreted by you the
computer just does the processing and
that's likely it like a model of the way
in which the right and the left
hemispheres understand one another or
the right hemisphere understands the
left at any rate so don't think the left
understands the right but it brings
knowledge information from experience
which the left hemisphere then can carry
out procedures on internally and then
gives that back to the right hemisphere
which must then reintegrate that with
everything else with the whole our
experience make sense of it so I think
those are important distinctions and I
think that rationality trying to be
reasonable trying to be objective it's
better to
a willingness to look at things from as
many points of view as possible and
assess which ones fit best rather than
to follow a line and say well my line of
reasoning leads there because you know
if your line of reasoning leads to a
dead end don't go down it go back and
try another cut so two things come to
mind immediately when you said that and
they converge in this the current work
I'm working on and the series I'm
working on which is people are talking
about dialogical reasoning and the idea
here is that we're and you know we're
typifying it we're exemplifying it right
now when you win and Sperber has a new
book that i pretended the co-author is
on the Enigma reason and lots of people
are not talking about this and something
I'm exploring very deeply that we lost
something when we moved with Aristotle
to the monologue treatise and when we
lost something that was when we had what
was that was being exemplified in the
Platonic dialogues I know you have
criticism there is something I want to
point here value the idea that like
because when we're in dialogue all of
the kinds of knowing are at play right
and it's not just the propositional
knowing we're doing off like you're
nodding and on gesturing and there's all
we're trying to engage all of the kinds
of knowing and as he just said we have
multiple perspectives and we can
actually you know I think what that
means and when when you do some
practices like I've done like the
circling practice or other things like
that what you what you get is this
tremendous sense of being able to access
something a third factor that a place
you can't get to on your own in your own
cognition and you get you get this right
you get this comprehensive sense Lowline
in fact argues and I think pretty
convincingly in his book that you know
when Plato is using the word Pesta me
where we get up and stomach from it
should not be translated as knowledge in
fact most of the time what Plato is
actually talking about is understanding
or understanding it means exactly this
well you know what kind of dynamic
convergence and then restructuring can
we get out of these multiple
perspectives coming into dialogue with
each other
so I think I think while I'm making a
claim I guess I think well the emergence
on the Internet of these dialogical
forums like this like rebel wisdom and
the increasing sense the the beginning
of what I see is a reflective census
people keep asking what is it we're
doing here what is it we're actually
doing here I think this is also part of
a cultural response to the meaning
crisis that we're starting to do all of
this because we're trying to figure out
we're trying to feel our way back to a
biological way of reasoning rather than
a monologic way of reasoning and I think
this is an important turn and I want to
be IIIi want to help as a scientist you
know bring theraph ocation to this but
also as a practitioner because I also do
participant observation I involved is
trying to help set up communities also
but to try and actually engender and
further this process greatly well I look
I wouldn't disagree with any of that I
except perhaps a little bit about FST me
but I don't want to get into I think
Plato did Socrates a great disservice by
writing the dialogues down except of
course if you had we wouldn't know
anything about Plato Socrates actually
you know didn't want these things to be
done on paper or as it were written at
all instead it had to be a live meeting
of minds and what and the seventh
epistle he talks about this but I think
you know there is richness to the the
the the the many words that there are in
Greek four kinds of knowledge not just
epidemia but particularly for aneesa's
which is a much more embodied pragmatic
understanding which takes whatever one
is intellectualizing about back into the
world and of course techne but that
sophia wisdom I mean from which we get
philosophy was a word that fantastically
applied from everything from you know a
philosopher down to
a ship right so Homer talks about ships
being built by the software of the
shipbuilding and theocritus talks about
a piece of cloth being woven by the
Sophia of the Weaver so I really love
that because again we're getting back to
this embodied sense of inhabiting the
world which is just not what we're doing
very much of the time these days I think
so I think so I think I need yeah I I
teach a course on the psychology of
wisdom and I do work on exactly this
kind of stuff and but the relationship
between Sophia phronesis also news
because news plays it important bridging
a troll between them you can see that
clearly in Plato and in and especially
clearly in Aristotle I would also say
that I think we have we have I wouldn't
want I don't want to dismiss your
criticism
Plato writing things down I think you're
right and what I want to say is that
that criticism of course was made in the
ancient world on mantissa knees of
course made it and then we get the
cynics and the stoic tradition coming
out of that and what's interesting is
stoicism especially cynicism is Lois's
and they put much more emphasis i mean
effect etus is all about don't tell me
what you're talking about
show me how you're transforming your
life right and so I think one one of the
things I want to do in this series is
can we take sort of the Platonic
dialogues but can we take the stoic
practices and stoicism is going through
a huge revival right now again not
coincidentally and I think we could look
then if you know allow me to fund we can
put the stoic developments right in the
Neoplatonic developments back into
dialogue and get back a better sense of
what this Socratic practice looked like
so that's part of what I'm actually
currently working on well that's great
and you came to me while you were
talking that actually we are
exemplifying at this moment the
possibility of philosophy that isn't
being written down it would be even
better if you were in the same room
because I think there's something that
happens when you're together with
somebody
you know there it is um yeah what I
would like to throw into that is that
all my life really ever since I first
discovered the pre-socratic philosophers
hmm I thought the greatest philosophy is
in the pre-socratic era
and this bloody Plato comes along with
this clod-hopping a still naked also
predestined and rules out the
possibility or seems to certainly
Aristotle did that actually a thing at
its opposite can equally be true now to
me that is the idea that nothing is
certain it's all changing an
interconnected and their offices flow
together and you know not seeing that is
a huge problem for modern culture we
need to get back to the pre-socratics
not just back to Plato Aristotle and all
that because one of the things that in a
way we don't appreciate the dark side of
what we do we live in an Enlightenment
or post enlightenment culture children
of the Enlightenment which believes that
everything can be made coherent with
everything else
it all fits into a nice logical picture
it's what Jung called the shadow or the
dark side to everything that appears
good there is a price to be paid in
something dark and everything that is
bad has it's possible redemption within
it and there's nothing so good that more
and more and more of it is just better
and nothing so bad that just a little
bit of it might help and that perception
is only we could just get as far as
acknowledging that things are not cut
and dried not black and white that there
is Obama recently said you know
ambiguous well that would really be a
very good place to be so um two things
about that
I've been practicing very many Taoist
practices now for for 29 years
now ISM is very much about that and it's
the dynamic interpenetration ice
that I see in in there later
especially when neoplatonism integrates
with aspects of Christianity in the work
of people like Guerra Gina and his
notion of dialectic I see something very
similar to what you're talking about and
so the fact that he was sort of
ostracized and a later declared a
heretic shows you that it did not come
foregrounded but nevertheless that there
there is definite I think there's
definitely elements especially towards
the later Neoplatonism where you see
something much more like what you're
talking about and that yeah a discussion
between that and Taoism has been very
possible for me in my life yeah so I'm
hoping I'm trying to share that with
people at large because I think that
kind of pluralistic dialogue is also
needed right now
so not just bringing multiple individual
perspectives into dialogue but bringing
multiple cultural perspectives wisdom
traditions into deep dialogue with each
other I think is also needed fantastic
I've just been they cost me more in
terms of Blood Sweat toil and tears than
anything else I've ever written and a
couple of chapters about the divine when
I first when I first met Rowan Williams
who you noticed lilo Jian who was our
Archbishop of Canterbury and after
writing the book you know we met and
talked and he said what are you thinking
of writing about and I said well if I
have enough hubris I'm thinking of
writing a short book about God and he
looked at me and he just went good luck
listen because a man it caused me a lot
of grief but in those chapters what I
was trying to do was show that there are
strands in Taoism and Zen Buddhism in
particular but also in Hinduism and in
the Western mystical tradition
particularly of course Meister Eckhart
and
irma meister eckhart again condemned as
a heretic and only probably got away
with it by dying in the nick of time but
I mean all these people were
exemplifying this kind of knowledge and
understanding but I think we're trying
to get towards and it's so present in
modern physics so I have you know
curiously I have this band of physicists
who read my work and write to me and say
this is just exactly on what we are
we're confronting and writing about
ourselves so that's very encouraging to
me okay well this is this is thrilling
for me first of all I want I don't know
if you read John Spencer's book the
eternal law because he talks about how
right at the beginning of the 20th
century many of these figures were
actually deeply influenced by the
Neoplatonic mystical tradition or
Vedanta in various ways arm and so he
goes through that and shows how very
deeply philosophical in the ancient
center full of sense of philosophy life
transformative wisdom these physicists
were deeply embedded in in NASH they
were in it but you should also know that
I mean the core I think we're maybe the
apex I don't know the combination I
don't know what the right now is here so
I'm but I mean I try to talk about this
idea of religio and well what happened
what happens when we get an experience
of sacredness when that religion becomes
something that we regard as sacred and
then right and then what is that what is
that putting us into relationship with
right because you're correct saying that
we grasp it is exactly not what does not
happen I'm in mystical experiences I
just ran an experiment in my lab where
we did a big and Turk survey on people
who have that mystical experience and
it's predictive of enhanced meaning in
life that's no surprise to you but it's
empirical evidence right but what's what
you might not know but you probably
suspect is what we have evidence it's
not the particular propositions people
come out of these experience with it's
the insight it's the process of
transformation right and what happens is
they get they get a sentence of the
really real and then they get they enter
into this aspirational project of trying
to conform themselves
because if they want to stay in touch
with their really real and that what's
going on there I've been doing a lot of
work on that and what's what's really
interesting is that has led me into a
lot of these kinds of discussions yet
with people that are coming out of the
Christian tradition and right and so and
so there's been this long discussion
we've been having very fruitful mutually
a respectful genuine Socratic dialogue
in my mind about sort of theism and
non-theism and getting into a deeper
discussion about that and I've been
trying to present non-theism as
something that's trying to break the
stranglehold the shared presuppositions
are both a sea of them and theism that
it's about belief that it's about a
supreme being right that we right and
all this and that that framing that
locks us into the debate is actually the
deeper problem and trying to get one
side to win over the other is actually
contributing to the meeting crisis
rather than resolving it well absolutely
and I would say you know the big divide
is not actually between sort of
believers and atheists but between
dogmatic fundamentalist believers with
their toads and their I'm right and all
the rest and those who have a genuine
openness because if you have that
genuine openness you can't be dogmatic
because the more you understand the more
you understand what you don't understand
you know it's it's the whole thing of
Nicolas accuser day dog take knowledge
less you know and I didn't it was just a
spasm of agreement I just said you made
no less but Nicolas of Cuza emphasizes
you get connected more you come into
greater conformity with God even though
you're knowing less I just I didn't I
just wanted to say that right learned
ignorance can strike people the wrong
way they can hear it the wrong way I
know but you make a very good point
which is there is there is knowing there
is not knowing
then there's a kind of Unknowing that is
the great achievement afterwards which
guns is like ignorant in the first
instance and it's the same thing as
innocence you know a child is innocent
we lose our innocence but a saint
regains our kind of innocence the far
side of experience so I would say it's
on the far side of that and that in fact
when you were talking about rationality
and people worrying about things being
irrational you know I was just thinking
about a very simple point but we need to
in state a word super irrational which
is that it's not irrational it's not you
know just knowing what's rational and
going against it for the sake of it or
because you can't see that but it's
acknowledging that something lies in a
realm which reason simply cannot reach
they can get so far and then it can't go
any further
so to have that knowledge is really
important and what I just wanted to add
is because I didn't mention this but the
the Kabbalah the the Jewish Kabbalah is
something that has transformed my life
in the last few years and of course not
Jewish by you know by origin but I got
to know about it and it has rung so many
bells with what I believe I've seen in
the neuro psychology literature about
the relationship between the hemispheres
I won't go into all that now you know
I've written about that's I think that's
fantastic I mean you do know I'm sure
that there's deep historical confluences
between the Neoplatonic tradition and
Kabbalah I mean verse Lewis talks about
a great length and I was going to point
to that term that I invoked earlier
because in the neo platonic tradition
you eventually get you know to noose and
then which is the on discursive
influential reasoning which is which is
a state of increasing conformity to the
real which isn't the same thing as
asserting propositions about the real
and then of course you know no right
right it's the okay yes exactly
the origin of no is it noticed in right
that's it you see it used in Homer Noah
system
sort of noticing getting that sense of
what salient er it's zero in my terms
its zeroing in on what's relevant so
that you're coupled to it appropriately
so that you can engage in the relevant
action behavior and so it's all about
this coupling and this this there's
participatory knowing this mutual
shaping and conformity and the rhesus I
think is the perspective of realization
and I mean both senses of the word
realization coming to awareness and
actualize in reality that's what I think
no rhesus is pointing to and I think the
Neoplatonic tradition I think that a big
corrective to the earlier Plato by
bringing no no II sis and news into
prominence in talking about how you
actually elite how you actually
cultivate wisdom and how you alleviate
the senses of separation and
disconnection because they really am I
have criticisms of the Neoplatonic
tradition I'm not trying to valorize
them unconditionally but the way they
point towards news and the way they
point to the issue of separation and
disconnection being the source of our
existential suffering I think these were
deep correctives deep correction yeah I
mean having said that I'm sure you
wouldn't
well I don't know whether you would
think I'm wrong or not but what I think
is so important is not to throw away the
baby with the bathwater there's a
tendency for one polarity of everything
is one you know when people say all is
one and they're very profound all is two
now all is many so the needs to be the
union of Union and device not just Union
or division and so but in any case
whatever to come back to there's
noticing I love the thing about noticing
and because it's something we don't do
much of nowadays partly because we're
living so much in the head we're in so
much of a hurry and we don't stop and
stare enough but when you do and train
yourself to see things you notice so
much more and you start to feel the
relationship with what it is you're
noticing now I have a strong belief that
it's not that reality is
made up by us but it's not that reality
just independently exists from us we
midwife reality into being our
consciousness which is never completely
separate from the consciousness of what
we're looking at brings out an aspect of
something and so we are actually not
just passive observers or recipients in
the cosmos we are actors in the cosmos
in bringing the cosmos into being I want
to respond to that very deeply first of
all I agree I think part of the
straightjacket I try to get out of the
series it's the the you know the locking
empiricism that the mind is tabula rasa
and the Rousseau Ian romanticism that
the world is applying a blank canvas
upon which we create our subjectivity I
think those are both wrong and so that's
why I've coined this phrase transgenic
tivity about trying to break out of the
subjectivity objectivity a polarization
of our epistemology so I think that's a
deep mistake and so I think that noticed
that that idea so this will sound like a
slight digression but one of my friends
and colleagues mark Lewis he's doing
some of the premiere work on addiction
right now and he's trying to replace the
disease model of addiction which does
not is not well supported by a lot of
data it's well funded by governments but
it's not well supported by data with a
learning model um and he calls it
reciprocal narrowing so it goes like
this let's say I get slightly drunk I
lose some cognitive flexibility and so I
can't notice as many options in the
world so the world starts to narrow a
bit I then internalize this which then
narrows and you get this reciprocal
narrowing until you can't notice - any
alternatives and you can't notice any
way in which you could be other than you
are and then you're the addict you're
trapped right and I think that's all
right um I think that's in fact I think
it's a brilliant account of addiction it
it supports much more of the empirical
data when I had life's with Mark I said
to him and that's why I brought in the
niels photonic tradition I said but mark
if there's reciprocal narrowing there
must be reciprocal opening
and he went you're right and I said that
you know and I think this is you know
the the whole idea of the anagen that
what we can do is we can put ourselves
into that and you call that that
openness in which right and I think this
is part of what what I see godsend stock
was circling how he's trying to enact
hiding area Heidegger's Alafaya right is
this reciprocal opening right and so and
and and and the work by Aaron and other
shows that's how you fall in love with
something like if you disclose something
and then I disclose and you do that
reciprocal opening where I open up what
I can be for you and that leads you to
open up what you can be for me and then
we reciprocally open we fall in love
with each other and so right and that
that I think that an agar get processed
right that reciprocal opening and you
can see it in flow States and right
that's that that that's one way of
trying to get this notion of noticing
and dialogue the biological relationship
into you know we can connect it with
practices or engage in and so I it leads
me to I mean I hesitate to say this
because it sounds like a Hallmark card
but I mean I see part of the project you
know of reuniting rationality in this
way with love so that we learned to fall
in love with reality again in a deep and
profound way that's fantastic and you
may know that or not that I have a
particular affection for the philosophy
of max Scheler you know who not much red
in the Anglo world where them and he
called humans human beings ends a man's
the being that loves and this is the bit
that was left out of Heidegger he was a
younger contemporary of hiding it hiding
a thought that Shayla was the most
important philosopher of the age as he
said at Sheila's funeral when when he
gave the iteration but the idea in
Shaler is not the love arises out of
acquiring knowledge but the knowledge
arises
disposition of love yeah you need that
it were to be open to something before
you can actually understand it if you
wait to know enough to open then you've
missed it and I think this is an idea
also in Pascal so it's not so mad and
it's also in Goethe so all of these
people saw that somehow our knowledge
depends on a on a loop of reciprocation
we're the kind of disposition towards
the world not a blind the opposition in
fact a very seeing one that is open
enough and you always have to take a
risk and that risk is that as you do in
love that it may be rejected and you may
be very hurt but nothing is achieved
without making a risk and the trouble
with the models we have by which we lead
our lives including our business lives
or socialites our intellectual lives is
that we can have a risk-free existence I
mean that's the fantasy and that every
kind of danger and risk should be
annihilated but we don't have near
enough danger and risk in our lives if
it was more we'd start to live properly
and and you see this in cultures and
people who have actually had to face
real risks and dangers what happens in
our culture is because a lot of people
really don't have any experience of it
we invent all kinds of risks and dangers
to which we are vulnerable from which we
must be protected this is a very bad way
to approach life yes I agree with that
very deeply I think our culture is
pursuing security at the expense of
Sophia in some pretty pleasant evening
when you were talking about that
reciprocal thing and it made me think in
your of the book the distinction you
make from between presencing and
representing because presence is kind of
knowing in which I am opening I'm
opening up to your presence as opposed
to forming a representation of you then
that's what I meant about the
perspective of knowing is governed by
normativity of presence as opposed to a
normativity of conviction so when I get
that you can see that actually you know
if all things you know probably
scientists we have to look for
interesting case studies but we aware
you see but in VR for
reality what people are actually looking
for in and here's what you might think
he's like well what mitt because they
what they crave is this a it's a sense
of presence people that's the normative
standard by the way if I get a sense of
being in the game that makes it a really
good game and you might think well it's
very similar to it's very similar to
that generates a sense of presence right
no no it's not it's neither necessary
nor sufficient what generates a sense of
presence is that reciprocal opening so
you can get it in things like Tetris
because you can get into the flow State
right you know right
again we get locked into a certain you
know representational purity if you'll
allow me that word and we lose right we
lose the continual emergence of
presencing which i think is much more
crucial to me tea making and to wisdom
cultivation will that distinction
between presencing and representation is
fundamental to my philosophy and like
you of the difference between the right
and the sphere to reach things presence
and the left when the sewage carries a
representation it's not from from cause
it's his idea of the map and the
territory and we miss stain on that
that's theoretical constructs for the
territory within mats and that is a huge
mistake and I don't know if you there
have read the bit where I talk about the
the experiment where people were asked
to about the truth or otherwise of
syllogisms and the porcupine is a monkey
did I read that I'm probably familiar
with it because I haven't read that book
in your book but David and Kim's they
did this wonderful study in which
subjects had one hemisphere at a time
knocked out and then they asked them
about the truth of the syllogism and the
syllogism of course is as you know that
there is two premises a statement that's
true another statement is true and then
something that follows from it but there
was a catch in each case one of the
premises was not true and so they asked
people to say is the conclusion correct
and to cut a long story short when
brain was intact and when the right
hemisphere alone was operating if one of
the statements that let the conclusion
was clearly false they said no the
conclusion is wrong but in the left
hemisphere state even if one of the
premises was clearly wrong contrary to
all their experience they've said the
conclusion was correct because that's
what it says on this piece of paper now
that seems a Goering Lee resonant to me
because I live in a world you know
working in hospitals where what's on the
piece of paper is more important than
what's actually happening between me and
the patient according to the managerial
culture in which one operated and I'm
sure the same thing happens in
universities and you know any big
organization totally I say all about
this research where you take studies in
cognitive science and cognitive science
that can't get published you don't
change them other than putting in an
fMRI picture of a brain you resubmit
them and then they get accepted for
publication yeah yeah so I think that's
very important so I'm wondering I I feel
like I have a bit of a responsibility
here and I approach you sure because you
did point to it earlier you do talk
about and you try to emphasize and you
brought it up
a few minutes ago that it's not the case
that you know the right hemisphere is
the right way to go or something like
that it's a dynamic integration of the
two you know this I think you give Jill
Bolte Taylor book my stroke of insight I
don't know if you've read I mean yeah so
you know she has the hemorrhage in the
left hemisphere it gets traumatized it
basically shuts down and everything
shifts into the right hemisphere and
that's not a wonderful existence either
right it's pretty horrific what's
interesting of course is she slowly
recuperates what I found particularly is
she she retains the ability because the
the the rehabilitation was when she it
was had full explicit awareness she can
she can step to the right she claims
whenever she needs to she can sort of
introspectively or int receptively shift
activation into the
I retained that as kind of a superpower
from a trauma she says he's transformed
her life you know that she's able to go
into this this place or leaves to see it
what we need to do is is see that the
fear is a very good servant but a very
poor master
then that is the that is the program
just gonna say that again because it
came up as a connection unstable what we
need to see is yeah yeah what we need to
see is that the left hemisphere is a
very good servant but a very poor master
and I believe that we've moved to the
position where we only attend to what
this poor servant good serve is telling
us as if it were the master and we're
ignoring what it is right hemisphere no
in fact we're being trained to be
ignored
do you know Christopher Alexander the
the architect and think fantastic no
anyway back in the 60s he did an
experiment of Radcliffe with a lot of
you know highly intelligent highly
educated young women and he asked them
to assemble a series of strips of black
and white sprites in any way they liked
and effectively what interested him was
that there are two ways of doing it one
is by a linear sequential way of
thinking the other is by a kind of
gestalt vision in which you see that
certain things go together to make
patterns and he thought that the you
know there might be a 50/50 about it but
they're actually being highly
intelligent they would naturally go for
the gestalt approach because it's more
the way in which we can understand
natural phenomena anything from the
growth of a fetus to the growth of the
spiral nebula in science what one is
doing is seeing patterns and
understanding them not just plodding
down a line of reasoning anyway 80% of
them group them in a totally serial way
and you know his question is well why
and I guess that it's the way in which
we're taught to think we're taught it's
not smart to pay attention to intuitions
and imagination it's only smart to keep
your nose on that thing and keep
plodding on right I think that's deeply
important
yeah it would be great too I think we're
kind of getting towards the the time on
this call so it'd be fantastic if you
have any kind of threads that you wanted
to kind of tie off before we we end this
edition I guess what's foremost in my
mind is I would like I would love to do
this again I found this I found it
there's enough common ground but there's
enough variation that where there's
excellent discussion happening here I
found it
well I found reciprocal opening
occurring I was gonna say to David I'm
better at opening up and closing down I
don't know how to close this
conversation tab closing your laptop I'm
walking away but that would be that
would be rude and I know you would do
that so I would like to that there was a
question that I was thinking about at
the beginning and I'm sure it's one that
I've asked John before and I've I've
heard him talk about but I'm not sure
I've heard but I was thinking I'd love
to hear your answer to this Ian do you
have a definition of wisdom what is
wisdom for you okay I think the
difficulty with wisdom is that no wise
person will tell you what it is or how
to achieve it it's one of those
paradoxical things it's like if you
really understand or begin to understand
God you don't understand
God and you know Agustin said well if
you understand then you haven't
understood it and I think wisdom falls
into that category which is why I'm a
little bit suspicious of studying wisdom
in the lab how can you it can't be
produced you know to order it can't be
measured and there aren't that many
people who get it it's rather like you
know if people say to me how do I get
wisdom is a bit like asking me how do I
get less self-conscious a very difficult
question to answer because all the
methods I will give you will make you
self-conscious
about it and and so it's it's it's a
problem but I think it's something you
recognize when you see it and I think
it's as much about a way of being as
anything else in fact it is a way of
being it's certainly not a knowledge or
an absence of knowledge or anything to
do with knowledge it's a kind of
approach to the world that can only come
with experience probably only comes with
a certain amount of suffering and comes
from a lot of self-examination and and
anybody who claims it hasn't got it so I
I agree with the in on that I mean I
think that the pragmatic
self-contradiction aspect of wisdom
McGee and Barbara commented on this a
long time ago in the 1990 paper that a
sure mark of somebody not being wise is
making the statement unwise so I agree
with that and I and I sort of agree with
the Platonic argument that we are always
finally as Sophia we're always we're
always lovers of wisdom we're in
dialogue together affording a mutual
aspiration a mutual love and we're
trying to get into that reciprocal
opening that ongoing conformity and so I
I do think that there are aspects I
think it's like studying love in the lab
you can't study love in the lab because
you can't sort of bring people and say
okay now do it love right I get that but
I mean you can you can so what you can
do is you can study components that seem
to I'm trying to use a word here that
won't tie me too much to it with the
mechanistic framework that you just like
in but you can study sort of components
or factors like I did earlier about how
reciprocal opening tends to engender
people coming into a state of love so
you can study the processes right and
the R and the constellation of processes
that seem to not produce statements of
I'm wise because I agree with you but
people do say and they get an A and they
do it with good reason and evidence and
interest subjective agreement I am wiser
than I was and I'm interested in what
when people say that
and what are they talking about and what
has happened and I agree with you they
don't typically mean I have now acquired
Theory X or Theory Y or even skill Y and
you can see all the Platonic dialogues
shooting all of those all of those
accounts of wisdom down no it's not that
it's not that it's not that instead what
they seem to do is they seem to point to
well again some of the things that I
think we were both discussing you know
getting a proper into you know a dynamic
integration between left and right and
also what we were exemplifying in this
kind of reciprocal opening and the idea
of trying to bring in multiple
perspectives get them talking to each
other not necessarily pursuing logical
coherence but pursuing something might
much more like biological reciprocity
and so I that's how I study it I study
it for example you know with people who
have mystical experiences do they find
that there were more aware in their life
of patterns of self-deception than
control groups these are questions of
course you can study scientifically
they're not going to give me the essence
of wisdom that's kind of a ridiculous
thing but they may give me if you'll
allow me they may give me a theory of
how I in fact explicitly argue that you
can only have a process theory of wisdom
you can't have a product theory you sort
of shouldn't try to tell me what the
product looks like but you can tell me a
lot about the process of becoming wise
and that's what I'm very much interested
in well you know it's just getting to
say wisdom isn't a thing it's a process
never ending journey is about them doing
things that you were certain of before
actually just not avoid completely
having anything to say but what could be
a path to wisdom it would be my favorite
Zen saying yes but and if only the
conversations have become so acrimonious
and so simplistic and extreme on the
internet workouts with yes but in the
world in which we don't have yes but you
appear you were cursed as an extremist
of another kind if you show any
hesitancy
accepting a certain position you are
certainly masters of Polaroids
but all the literacy conversation was
going on in the area of hesitancy and
actually a philosopher that I I knew
like and greatly admired Roger Scruton
died not long ago and when he was asked
about the essence of philosophy I think
you said hesitancy so I you know I think
that's a good one well I mean I could
pick up on your point I think we've
dropped too much into adversarial
processing and to pick up something you
emphasized in your book and I emphasize
in my work
we've lost opponent processing we've
lost the idea that we can come at things
from opposite angles but we can be
mutually committed to a process of
mutual self correction rather than
victory over the other and I think
that's what I would be trying to move
towards wonderful this has been a really
fascinating conversation thank you both
for making the time and for showing us
the process of kind of thinking in real
time it was really beautiful to watch so
thank you thank you David so much and
it's been a great pleasure
really great I hope at some point we can
repeat it as the tech revolution
continues to destroy old media the
Internet is fueling a new intellectual
awakening television made people look
stupider than they were it turns out
that people are smarter with longer
attention spans then we thought I'm a
journalist and filmmaker for many years
I made documentaries for the likes of
the BBC and channel 4 but I don't think
the mainstream media can provide the
level of analysis and insight we need
for the extraordinary time as we're
going through where the old structures
that made sense of the world break down
like we're entering just entering into
the underwear
and it's a descent we're feeling
everything starting to shake and the
center cannot hold
and when our ways of thinking break down
it's the rebels and the Renegades who
dare to think differently who are needed
to reboot the system and so what's
happening is that people are perceiving
because it's becoming increasingly
obvious that all of these artifacts of
the way that we've gone about doing
civilization are breaking down and
failing in a way that is no longer easy
to pretend isn't happening and so as a
consequence this triggers a deep
visceral sense and that's a good thing
right because that deep visceral sense
is the return to the aluminum the return
to the mystery the shift that we are on
the precipice of is not like the shift
from the Dark Ages to the Enlightenment
it's like more like a shift from single
cell to multicellular life these are the
people and ideas rebel wisdom is
searching out to try to make sense of
the growing chaos the evolution screwed
up it handed us the tools to recognize
that we don't have to value the game
that it is playing and that we can now
repurpose the hardware to something
that's actually worthwhile that's what I
actually have hope in is that if enough
people can come to that realization then
then we wake up and not in some bullshit
evangelical megachurch kind of way of
being born again but in in a truly
initiatory way being born again of like
I know my purpose I know my part and I'm
willing to practice resurrection I'm
willing to offer my life fully and
freely in love in every moment and then
we're invincible like then we can turn
things on a dime it's also about trying
to create a new form of conversation one
based on genuine dialogue letting go of
ideology and fix ideas so we want to be
a place that hosts this new form of
conversation both online and at our
events check out our films join the
conversation and to get early access to
some great films and exclusive content
please consider supporting us on patreon
you